What if I told you there was something
that you can do right now that would have
an immediate positive benefit for your brain,
including your mood and your focus?
And what if I told you that same thing
could actually last a long time and protect
your brain from different conditions like depression, Alzheimer's disease or dementia?
Would you do it?
Yes, I am talking about the powerful effects
of physical activity that is simply moving your body
Has immediate, long lasting and protective benefits
For your brain and that can last for the rest of your life.
So what I want to do today is tell you a story
About how I use my deep understanding of neuroscience
As a professor to essentially do an experiment on myself
In which I discovered the science underlying why exercise
Is the most transformative thing that you can do for your brain today.
Now, as a neuroscientist, I know that our brain,
That is the thing in our head right now,
That is the most complex structure known to humankind.
But it's one thing to talk about the brain
and it's another to see it.
So here is a real preserved human brain
and it's going to illustrate two key areas
that we're going to talk about today.
The first is the prefrontal cortex right behind your forehead
critical for things like decision making, focus, attention,
and your personality.
The second key area is located in the temporal lobe shown right here.
You have two temporal lobes on your brain,
The right and the left.
And deep in the temporal lobe is a key structure
critical for your ability to form and retain
new long-term memories for facts and events.
And that structure is called the hippocampus.
So I've always been fascinated with the hippocampus.
How could it be that an event that lasts just a moment?
Say, your first kiss or the moment your first child was born
can form a memory that has changed your brain
that lasts an entire lifetime.
That's what I want to understand.
I wanted to start and record the activity
of individual brain cells in the hippocampus
as subjects were forming new memories
and essentially trying to decode how those brief bursts
of electrical activity, which is how neurons communicate with each other.
How those brief bursts either allowed us to form
a new memory or did not.
But a few years ago I did something very unusual in science.
As a full professor of neural science,
I decided to completely switch my research program
because I encountered something that was so amazing
with the potential to change so many lives
that I had to study it.
I discovered and I experienced the brain-changing effects of exercise.
And I did it in a completely inadvertent way.
I was actually at the height of all the memory work that I was doing. Data was pouring in.
I was becoming known in my field for all of this memory work
and it should have been going great.
It was scientifically.
But when I stuck my head out of my lab door, I noticed something.
I had no social life.
I spent too much time listening to those brain cells in a dark room by myself.
I didn't move my body at all.
I gained 25 pounds and actually took me many years to realize it was actually by myself because I hadn't socialized.
And I came back thinking, oh my god, I was the weakest person on that trip.
And I came back with a mission.
I said I never going to feel like the weakest person on a revolving trip again.
And that's what made me go to the gym.
And I focused my type A personality on going to all the exercise classes at the gym.
I tried everything.
I went too hard.
But what I noticed is that after every sweat-inducing workout that I tried,
I had this great mood boost and this great energy boost.
And that's what kept me going back to the gym.
Well, I started feeling stronger.
I started feeling better. I even lost those 25 pounds.
And now fast forward, a year and a half into this regular exercise program.
And I noticed something that really made me sit up and take notice.
I was sitting at my desk writing a research grant.
And a thought went through my mind that had never gone through my mind before.
And that thought was, grant writing is going well today.
And all the scientists always laugh.
And I say that because grant writing never goes well.
It is so hard. You're always pulling your hair out trying to come up with that million-dollar winning idea.
But I realized that the grant writing was going well
because I was able to focus and maintain my attention for longer than I had before.
And my long-term memory would always seem to be better in me.
And that's when I put it together.
Maybe all that exercise that I had included and added to my life was changing my brain.
Maybe I didn't experiment on myself without even knowing it.
So as a curious neuroscientist, I went to the literature
to see what I could find about what we knew about the effects of exercise on the brain.
And what I found was an exciting and growing literature
that was essentially showing everything that I noticed in myself.
Better mood, better energy, better memory, better attention.
And the more I learned, the more I realized how powerful exercise was,
which eventually led me to the big decision to completely shift my research focus.
And so now, after several years of really focusing on this question,
I've come to the following conclusion that exercise is the most transformative thing
That you can do for your brain today for the following three reasons.
Number one, it has immediate effects on your brain. A single workout that you do
will immediately increase levels of neurotransmitters like dopamine, serotonin, and noradrenaline.
That is going to increase your mood right after that workout.
Exactly what I was feeling. My lab showed that a single workout
can improve your ability to shift and focus attention.
And that focus improvement will last for at least two hours.
And finally, studies have shown that a single workout
will improve your reaction times, which basically means that you are going to be faster
at catching that cup of Starbucks that falls off the counter, which is very, very important.
But these immediate effects are transient. They help you right after.
What you have to do is do what I did, that is change your exercise range to regime.
Increase your cardiovascular function to get the long lasting effects.
And these effects are long lasting because exercise actually changes
the brain's anatomy, physiology, and function.
Let's start with my favorite brain area, the hippocampus.
The hippocampus or exercise actually produces brand new brain cells,
new brain cells in the hippocampus, that actually increase its volume
as well as improve your long-term memory.
And that includes a new and me. Number two, the most common finding in neuroscience studies,
Looking at the effects of exercise, long-term exercise is improved attention function.
It depends on your prefrontal cortex. You not only get better focus and attention,
but the volume of the hippocampus increases as well.
And finally, you not only get immediate effects on mood with exercise,
but those last for a long time, so you get long-lasting increases
in those good mood neurotransmitters. But really, the most transformative thing that exercise
will do is its protective effects on your brain.
Here you can think about the brain like a muscle.
The more you're working out, the bigger and stronger your hippocampus and prefrontal cortex get.
Why is that important? Because the prefrontal cortex and the hippocampus are the two areas
That are most susceptible to neurodegenerative diseases and normal cognitive decline in aging.
So with increased exercise over your lifetime, you're not going to cure dementia or Alzheimer's disease.
But what you're going to do is you're going to create the strongest, biggest hippocampus and prefrontal cortex.
So it takes longer for these diseases to actually have an effect.
You can think of exercise therefore as a supercharged 401k for your brain.
And it's even better because it's free.
So this is a point in the talk where everybody says
That sounds so interesting, Wendy,
But I really only want to know one thing.
And that is just tell me the minimum amount of exercise.
I need to get all these changes.
So I'm going to tell you the answer to that question. First, good news.
You don't have to become a triathlete to get these effects.
The rule of thumb is you want to get three to four times a week exercise
Minimum 30 minutes and exercise session
And you want to get aerobic exercise in that is get your heart rate up.
And the good news is you don't have to go to the gym
To get a very expensive gym membership.
Add an extra walk around the block in your power walk.
You see stairs? Take stairs.
And power vacuuming can be as good as the aerobics class
That you're going to take at the gym.
So I have gone from memory pioneer to exercise explorer.
From going into the innermost workings of the brain
To try and understand how exercise can improve our brain function.
And my goal in my lab right now is to go beyond that rule of thumb
That I just gave you: three to four times a week, 30 minutes.
I want to understand the optimum exercise prescription for you
At your age, at your fitness level,
For your genetic background to maximize the effects of exercise today.
And also to improve your brain and protect your brain the best
For the rest of your life.
But it's one thing to talk about exercise and it's another to do it.
So I'm going to invoke my power as a certified exercise instructor
To ask you all to stand up.
We're going to do just one minute of exercise.
It's called response.
Just do what I do.
Say what I say and make sure you don't punch your neighbor. Okay? Music.
5, 6, 7, 8. It's right left, right left.
And I say, I am strong now. Let's hear you. I am strong now.
Ladies, I am Wonder Woman's Royal, let's hear you.
New move, uppercuts, right and left.
I am inspired now, you say it.
Let's move, pull it down, right and left, right and left.
I say, I am on fire now, you say it.
I am on fire now. And done, okay? Good job.
Thank you.
I want to leave you with one last thought,
and that is bringing exercise in your life will not only
Give you a happier and more protective life today,
But it will protect your brain from insurable diseases
And in this way it will change the trajectory of your life for the better.
Thank you very much.