What  if  I  told  you  there  was  something
that  you  can  do  right  now  that  would  have
an  immediate positive  benefit  for  your  brain,
including  your  mood  and  your  focus?
And  what  if  I  told  you  that  same thing
could  actually  last  a  long  time  and  protect
your  brain  from  different  conditions  like  depression, Alzheimer's  disease  or  dementia?
Would  you  do  it?
Yes, I  am  talking  about  the  powerful  effects
of  physical  activity  that  is  simply  moving  your  body
has  immediate, long  lasting  and  protective benefits
for  your  brain  and  that  can  last  for  the  rest  of  your  life.
So  what  I  want  to  do  today is  tell  you  a  story
about  how  I  use  my  deep  understanding  of  neuroscience
as  a  professor  of to  essentially  do  an  experiment  on  myself
in  which  I  discovered  the  science  underlying  why  exercise
is  the  most  transformative  thing  that  you  can  do for  your  brain  today.
Now, as  a  neuroscientist,I  know  that  our  brain,
that  is  the  thing  in  our  head  right  now,
that  is  the  most  complex  structure known  to  humankind.
But  it's  one  thing  to  talk  about  the  brain
and  it's  another  to  see  it.
So  here  is  a  real  preserve  of  human  brain
and  it's  going  to  illustrate  two  key  areas
that  we're going  to  talk  about  today.
The  first  is  the  prefrontal  cortex  right  behind  your  forehead
critical for  things  like  decision  making, focus, attention,
and  your  personality.
The  second  key  area  is located  in  the  temporal  lobe shown  right  here.
You  have  two  temporal  lobes  on  your  brain,
the  right and  the  left.
And  deep  in  the  temporal  lobe  is  a  key  structure
critical  for  your  ability  to  form and  retain
new  long-term memories  for  facts  and  events.
And  that  structure  is  called  the  hippocampus.
So  I've  always  been  fascinated  with  the  hippocampus.
How  could  it  be  that  an  event  that  lasts just  a  moment?
Say, your  first  kiss  or  the  moment  your  first  child  was  born
can  form  a  memory that  has  changed  your  brain
that  lasts  an  entire  lifetime.
That's  what  I  want  to  understand.
I  wanted  to  start  and  record  the  activity
of  individual  brain  cells  in  the  hippocampus
as  subjects  were  forming  new  memories
and  essentially  trying  to  decode  how  those  brief  bursts
of  electrical  activity  which  is  how  neurons  communicate with  each  other.
How  those  brief  bursts either  allowed  us  to  form
a  new  memory  or  did  not.
But  a  few  years  ago  I  did  something  very unusual  in  science.
As  a  full  professor  of  neural  science,
I  decided  to  completely  switch my  research  program
because  I  encountered  something  that  was  so  amazing
with  the  potential to  change  so  many  lives
that  I  had  to  study  it.
I  discovered  and  I  experienced  the  brain changing  effects of  exercise.
And  I  did  it  in  a  completely  inadvertent  way.
I  was  actually  at the  height  of  all  the  memory  work  that  I  was  doing. Data  was  pouring  in.
I  was  becoming known  in  my  field  for  all  of  this  memory  work
and  it  should  have  been  going  great.
It  was scientifically.
But  when  I  stuck  my  head  out  of  my  lab  door, I  noticed  something.
I  had  no  social life.
I  spent  too  much  time  listening  to  those  brain  cells  in  a  dark  room  by  myself.
I  didn't move  my  body  at  all.
I  gained  25  pounds  and  actually  took  me  many  years  to  realize  it  was  actually by  myself  because  I  hadn't  socialized.
And  I  came  back  thinking, oh  my  god, I  was  the  weakest person  on  that  trip.
And  I  came  back  with  a  mission.
I  said  I  never  going  to  feel  like  the  weakest person  on  a  revolving  trip  again.
And  that's  what  made  me  go  to  the  gym.
And  I  focused  my  type a  personality  on  going  to  all  the  exercise  classes  at  the  gym.
I  tried  everything.
I  went  to hard.
But  what  I  noticed  is  that  after  every  sweat-inducing workout  that  I  tried,
I  had  this  great  move  boost  and  this  great  energy  boost.
And  that's  what  kept  me  going  back to  the  gym.
Well, I  started  feeling  stronger.
I  started  feeling  better. I  even  lost  that  25  pounds.
And  now  fast  forward, a  year  and  a  half  into  this  regular  exercise  program.
And  I  noticed  something that  really  made  me  sit  up  and  take  notice.
I  was  sitting  in  my  desk  writing  a  research  grant.
And  a  thought  went  through  my  mind  that  had  never  gone  through  my  mind  before.
And  that  thought  was gee, grant  writing  is  going  well  today.
And  all  the, yeah, all  the  scientists  always  laugh.
And  I  say  that  because  grant  writing  never  goes  well.
It  is  so  hard. You're  always  pulling  your out  trying  to  come  up  with  that  million  dollar  winning  idea.
But  I  realized  that  the  grant  writing was  going  well
because  I  was  able  to  focus  and  maintain  my  attention  for  longer  than  I  had  before.
And  my  long-term memory  would  always  study  in  my  own  lab, seem  to  be  better  in  me.
And  that's  when  I  put  it  together.
Maybe  all  that  exercise  that  had  included  and  added  to  my  life was  changing  my  brain.
Maybe  I  didn't  experiment  on  myself  without  even  knowing  it.
So  as  a curious  neuroscientist, I  went  to  the  literature
to  see  what  I  could  find  about  what  we  knew  about the  effects  of  exercise  on  the  brain.
And  what  I  found  was  an  exciting  and  a  growing  literature
that  was  essentially  showing  everything  that  I  noticed  in  myself.
Better  mood, better  energy,better  memory, better  attention.
And  the  more  I  learned, the  more  I  realized  how  powerful  exercise was,
which  eventually  led  me  to  the  big  decision  to  completely  shift  my  research  focus.
And  so now, after  several  years  of  really  focusing  on  this  question,
I've  come  to  the  following  conclusion that  exercise  is  the  most  transformative  thing
that  you  can  do  for  your  brain  today  for  the  following three  reasons.
Number  one, it  has  immediate  effects  on  your  brain, a  single  workout  that  you  do
will  immediately  increase  levels  of  neurotransmitters  like  dopamine, serotonin, and  nor  adrenaline.
That  is  going  to  increase  your  mood  right  after  that  workout.
Exactly  what  I  was  feeling. My lab  showed  that  a  single  workout
can  improve  your  ability  to  shift  and  focus  attention.
And  that focus  improvement  will  last  for  at  least  two  hours.
And  finally, studies  have  shown  that  a  single workout
will  improve  your  reaction  times, which  basically  means  that  you  are  going  to  be  faster
at catching  that  cup  of  Starbucks  that  falls  off  the  counter, which  is  very, very  important.
But  these  immediate  effects  are  transient. They  help  you  right  after.
What  you  have  to  do  is  do what  I  did  that  is  change  your  exercise  range  to  regime.
Increase  your  cardiovascular  function to  get  the  long  lasting  effects.
And  these  effects  are  long  lasting  because  exercise  actually  changes
the  brain's  anatomy, physiology, and  function.
Let's  start  with  my  favorite  brain  area, the  hippocampus.
The  hippocampus  or  exercise  actually  produces  brand  new  brain  cells,
new  brain  cells  in  the  hippocampus,that  actually  increase  its  volume
as  well  as  improve  your  long-term memory, okay?
And  that includes  a  new  and  me. Number  two, the  most  common  finding  in  neuroscience  studies,
looking  in  the  effects  of  exercise, long-term exercise, is  improved  attention  function,
dependent  on  your  prefrontal  cortex. You  not  only  get  better  focus  and  attention,
but  the  volume of  the  hippocampus  increases  as  well.
And  finally, you  not  only  get  immediate  effects  of mood  with  exercise,
but  those  last  for  a  long  time, so  you  get  long  lasting  increases
in those  good  mood  neurotransmitters. But  really, the  most  transformative  thing  that  exercise
will  do  is  its  protective  effects  on  your  brain.
Here  you  can  think  about  the  brain  like  a  muscle.
The  more  you're  working  out, the  bigger  and  stronger  your  hippocampus  and  prefrontal  cortex  gets.
Why  is  that  important? Because  the  prefrontal  cortex  and  the  hippocampus  are  the  two  areas
that  are  most  susceptible  to  neurodegenerative  diseases  and  normal  cognitive  decline  in  aging.
So  with  increased  exercise  over  your  lifetime, you're  not  going  to  cure  dementia  or  Alzheimer's  disease.
But  what  you're  going  to  do  is  you're  going  to  create  the  strongest, biggest  hippocampus  in  prefrontal cortex.
So  it  takes  longer  for  these  diseases  to  actually  have  an  effect.
You  can  think  of  exercise therefore  as  a  supercharged  401k  for  your  brain.
And  it's  even  better  because  it's  free.
So  this  is  a  point  in  the  talk  where  everybody  says
that  sounds  so  interesting, Wendy,
but  I  really  only  want  to  know  one  thing.
And  that  is  just  tell  me  the  minimum  amount  of  exercise.
I  need  to  get  all  these  changes.
So  I'm  going  to  tell  you  the  answer  to  that  question. First, good  news.
You  don't  have  to  become  a  triathlete  to  get  these  effects.
The  rule  of  thumb  is  you  want  to  get  three  to  four  times  a  week  exercise
minimum  30  minutes and  exercise  session
and  you  want  to  get  aerobic  exercise  in  that  is  get  your  heart  rate  up.
And  the  good  news  is  you  don't  have  to  go  to  the  gym
to  get  a  very  expensive  gym  membership.
Add  an  extra  walk  around  the  block  in  your  power  walk.
You  see  stairs? Take  stairs.
And  power  vacuuming  can  be  as  good  as  the  aerobics  class
that  you're  going  to  take  at  the  gym.
So  I  have  gone  from  memory, pioneer  to  exercise, explore.
From  going  into  the innermost  workings  of  the  brain
to  try  and  understand  how  exercise  can  improve  our  brain  function.
And  my  goal  in  my  lab  right  now  is  to  go  beyond  that  rule  of  thumb
that  I  just  gave  you  three  to  four  times  a  week  30  minutes.
I  want  to  understand  the  optimum  exercise  prescription  for  you
at  your  age, at  your  fitness  level,
for  your  genetic  background  to  maximize  the  effects  of  exercise  today
and  also  to  improve  your brain  and  protect  your  brain  the  best
for  the  rest  of  your  life.
But  it's  one  thing  to  talk  about exercise  and  it's  another  to  do  it.
So  I'm  going  to  invoke  my  power  as  a  certified  exercise instructor
to  ask  you  all  to  stand  up.
We're  going  to  do  just  one  minute  of  exercise.
It's calling  response.
Just  do  what  I  do.
Say  what  I  say  and  make  sure  you  don't  punch  your  neighbor, okay? Music.
5, 6, 7, 8. It's  right  left, right  left.
And  I  say, I  am  strong  now. Let's  hear  you. I  am  strong  now.
Ladies, I  am  Wonder  Woman's  Royal, let's  hear  you.
New  move, upper  cuts, right  and  left.
I  am  inspired  now, you  say  it.
Let's  move, pull  it  down, right  and  left, right  and  left.
I  say, I  am  on  fire  now, you  say  it.
I  am  on  fire  now. And  done, okay? Good  job.
Thank  you.
I  want  to  leave  you  with  one  last  thought,
and  that  is  bringing  exercise  in  your  life  will  not  only
give  you  a  happier  and  more  protective life  today,
but  it  will  protect  your  brain  from  insurable  diseases
and  in  this  way  it  will  change the  trajectory  of  your  life  for  the  better.
Thank  you  very  much.